So we're going to wrap up this section
talking a little bit more about what we would do
in order to get the instructions,
the machine language instructions,
instead of coming from a little switch
which is completely fake, but instead coming from the memory.
And so to do that, we look a little bit more
into computer architecture.
We talked before about the ALU,
the arithmetic and logic unit, as well as the registers.
So the ALU has like an adder in it,
maybe a multiplier or a comparison module, all in hardware.
Then we have registers which have, you know,
bits in them like numbers and their temporary storage.
And in addition, we're going to talk a little more now
about the logic.
Now the load and store, the way we're going to do it
goes to and from registers for like data memory,
but for program memory, there's a couple of things
that the CPU uses to control program memory.
So one is the PC or program counter register.
So this is a register that points to the next instruction
we're supposed to execute.
So the CPU, when it's ready to execute an instruction,
it says, oh, the PC tells me where to load it.
So I'm going to load that instruction from the memory
into CIR, current instruction register.
And that's just some bits, zeros and one.
And then I mentioned the idea of a decoder.
And in the previous example, we had some AND gates
that were in a sense our decoder.
So when you have a real CPU,
it has a lot more than two instructions.
And the decoder is looking at the pattern of bits
in the instruction, decoding it,
and then sending logic to the ALU and the registers
to activate the right thing to get the right thing to happen.
So maybe we're going to add two registers together
and store the result in a different register, okay?
And the decoder sees that instruction
that is the add two registers
and store in another register instruction.
And then the decoder sees the pattern of that,
and then it activates the right registers,
the right arithmetic logic unit,
and then causes the instruction to happen
in one or a couple of clock cycles,
depending on how difficult it is.
In the previous example, we had like a zero to reset
and a one to add one every clock cycle.
So it incremented or it stopped, it went back to zero.
But in reality, you need a series
of machine language instructions,
like set register four to zero,
compare register four to zero,
increment register four, decrement register four.
And so there are binary patterns,
which are part of the documentation of a microprocessor.
So if the decode unit looks at 0100 for the instruction,
it says, oh, that's a zero instruction.
And then RRR is three bits for a register
from zero through seven.
So you're setting register three to zero.
And so these are just simple patterns,
and they might seem really complex to you,
but in some ways, they're actually really easy.
The number of things you can do
in this machine language is really limited.
Now it makes programs a lot more verbose.
And usually we don't even write the zeros and ones,
we write this stuff called assembly,
which we'll talk about coming up.
Or we write C, which is a higher level language
that then generates assembly,
which generates machine language.
Or we take a language like Python,
which sort of almost completely separates us
from the machine language.
But then Python itself is written in machine language
so that it's really fast.
So coming up next, we're going to design
a very simple central processing unit.
I call it the CDC 8512, inspired by my first computer,
the Control Data Corporation, CDC 6500.
It'll have a complete architecture.
It'll be completely defined.
It'll have a program counter.
It'll have an instruction register.
And we will write real, very small programs
in CDC 8512 machine code,
and then run them on an emulator.
(upbeat music)